*13 REASONS Why*
Season 03  Episode 13
Episode Title:
"Let the Dead Bury the Dead"
Sync corrections  by  srjanapala
♪ Up at night.
feeling dumb ♪
♪ Am I all alone? ♪
♪ Hide away from it all
In a stranger's home ♪
♪ Is it me. is it you?
Can I trust myself? ♪
♪ I need some help.
I'm fine. don't ask ♪
♪ The truth is
I'm nightmares underneath ♪
♪ It's useless ♪
♪ Oh. well.
who cares? ♪
Be cool. all right?
They're holding you
to make you sweat.
They're not gonna press felony charges
for steroids.
Okay? Just sit tight.
Give me a couple hours.
Five minutes.
Hey. Dad.
Sit.
♪ Welcome the new Great Depression ♪
Your mother.
she hasn't stopped crying
since they picked you up.
Sorry.
I bust my ass
for this family.
and this is what you do?
- Answer me!
- What? What answer do you want?
Is it true?
What they're saying?
- What are they saying?
- You damn well know.
They're saying you assaulted a kid.
That you sexually assaulted a kid.
A boy.
- That true?
- No. it wasn't sexual assault.
I was messing with him.
You were messing with him?
The way they said?
Why would you do that shit?
To a boy?
You some kind of faggot?
What if I was. Dad?
What if I was?
You're going to prison.
You know what they do
to guys like you in there?
What do they do? Describe it.
You're gonna get beat to shit.
At the minimum.
They will beat you down.
Yeah. well at least none of them
will be my dad.
You a faggot?
Sure.
You got one on me. Jensen.
I've never had one of those.
Yeah. I'm breaking your records
all the time.
It's brutal.
but it's better than a jail cell.
We had to agree to it
to get the prosecutor into court
this morning and get you RoR'd.
- I'm not complaining.
- So. what?
- He can't leave the outhouse?
- He's not on house arrest.
It's a GPS unit.
So. they can track him to school.
the library.
- wherever he's cleared to go.
- Wait. school?
You have a meeting
with the new counselor.
She'll do an evaluation
and tell the school district
if you're okay to come back.
Like. to see if I'm still homicidal?
Enough with that talk.
Okay? Your state of mind counts.
Now. but especially at trial.
What if it doesn't even go to trial?
I mean. what if they come up
with new evidence or a new...
a new witness?
Is that why you went to see Seth Massey
the other night?
I...
Uh...
- I thought he could help.
- Unlikely.
He was arrested
on parole violations.
He's going away
for a long time.
- How did you know that I was with him?
- They had detectives tailing you.
You can assume they will
from now on.
So. watch your back.
Both of you.
School in ten.
Fuck!
I thought he could get rid of the dealer.
So I could be your alibi.
I'm going to prison.
For the rest of my life.
You most definitely are not.
I've got to tell you something.
It's heavy shit.
Ani called me last night.
She was with Jess.
Hey. Andrew. Walker crime scene.
what did we get for footprints?
Not a lot. There was rain that weekend.
So. we mostly had scuff marks
from the struggle.
Right. this here shows a limp. right?
Yeah. which that Dempsey kid...
So. that answers that.
Right. so the kid that was in the fight
here was dragging his right foot.
like Zach would've.
What about this one?
Doesn't this show
a left foot being dragged?
Yeah. possibly.
Or maybe we're looking at it wrong.
There's not one complete print.
I wouldn't take it to court.
All right.
What about tire treads?
- You were out again all night.
- Not all night.
Jessica Davis needed some help.
We've got a test.
Mrs. Walker saw you
in the window of the coffee shop
with a girl and a boy.
Yeah. Justin Foley was
there. too.
We're all in the
same history class.
I will assume that is a lie.
The police called this morning.
- What?
- Deputy Standall.
They want to see you again.
I told them
we would be there this evening.
I see.
All right.
- Amorowat. I told you not to get involved.
- Mum. I know. I know.
But you brought me
into this country.
and I'm glad you did.
and now you have to let me live
in this country.
And take care of my friends.
and my friends
needed me last night.
Did they also lie to the police?
How can you be sure
this boy didn't commit the crime?
Because I know him. Mum!
And he's good.
You mustn't lie
to the police again.
What? What is it?
Fucking Standall wants
to talk to me again.
- Shit! Why?
- Does it matter?
Look. I got an all-cash offer
to sell the garage
- to the guy who owns Maverick's.
- What about the title?
He's gonna file
a new title himself.
transfer it over
to his holding company. clean it up.
- He's cool with it.
- Jesus. Tony. That's fraud.
You're gonna talk to me
about fraud?
They have Clay for murder.
Once they figure out
he's innocent.
- they're gonna work their way...
- How do you know?
How do you know
that he is innocent?
Tell me the truth about that night.
About Homecoming.
- I told you the truth.
- I...
Shit! One second.
You kidding?
It's Tim Pozzi.
That dealer that got banned from City Gym.
I have to kick him out.
You heard Monty was arrested
last night?
Yeah.
You okay?
No one's said anything to you or anything?
I mean. nothing bad.
People are...
still kinda being nice to me.
St. George.
Um...
I'll be right back.
The prosecutor doesn't believe
you pose a threat
to your classmates.
So. we're here today to determine
if returning to class
is the best thing for you.
What makes you all think
I want to return?
- You don't want to come back?
- What good has this place ever done me?
What good has high school
done anyone?
I feel like all I've learned
these last few years is life is fucked.
Don't try and help anyone.
- I'm sorry you feel that way.
- Don't you?
I mean.
how do you do it?
- Do what?
- Your job.
How do you show up here
every day
hoping to make it better. knowing
nothing ever changes?
Tyler Down told me the reason
he came to see me in the first place
last spring was
because of you.
Is that true?
I guess... I guess so.
So what?
So. you said
things don't get better.
But it does. And Tyler has.
in no small part because of you.
Clay. you asked me how I do it.
It's easy. I show up.
Every day. I show up.
no matter what.
Good days or bad.
because that's all we can do.
And that's all you can do.
So...
you think you can show up?
- You told Clay?
- Yeah.
Yeah. I did. But listen.
there's something new that happened.
Okay. me first.
The police called me in again.
They want to see me today.
Shit.
Come here.
You're gonna want to hear this...
before you talk to the police.
Jesus. Ani.
I know. but it can help
when I go to the sheriff.
No. don't go down there.
Don't do that!
Clay. I promise
I will figure this out.
If I can't make things better.
I won't make it worse.
Don't go down there.
Y-Y-You may think you have a plan.
but you're jumping into it head first.
- You're not listening to reason.
- Okay. First. I do have a plan.
And-And second.
are you really the person to criticize me
for being headstrong and stubborn?
It's just. what if it doesn't work?
Listen. I need you
to hold up your end.
A confession at this point
fucks us up!
- Right?
- No. I know.
Clay. I've told you
what you need to know.
You can do this.
You trust me.
don't you?
I... I trust you.
Sit right there.
Can I get you some water
or anything?
No. thank you.
I wasn't expecting you
until later.
Before we begin.
if you're expecting
I'm gonna help you
prove Clay Jensen guilty.
you'll be disappointed.
- 'Cause I don't believe he is.
- You don't?
Just so you know.
you're facing the reality
that most people believe
he is guilty.
Do you still want to talk?
I do.
Okay.
Do you mind?
Begin at the beginning.
Who you are. what school you're from
and why you're here.
My name is
Amorowat Anysia Achola.
You can call me
Ani.
I'm a senior
at Liberty High School.
You don't have to do that
anymore.
It's an interesting place.
I'm never playing football
ever again.
Justin told me
you went to the sheriff.
You didn't have to do that.
- Thank you.
- I didn't do it for you.
I did it
because it was the right thing to do.
Yeah. but sometimes it's hard
to know what the right thing is.
Listen. Zach.
Either way.
you put yourself on the line.
I'm gonna do the same.
You deserve to know
the truth.
Bryce Walker did hurt
a lot of people.
Zach and Chloe. certainly.
But I soon realized
the one he hurt the most
was Jessica Davis.
You wanna talk about
Jessica Davis?
You need to understand
everyone had their reasons.
And you need to understand
what those reasons are.
Everyone had a reason.
- including you?
- Including me.
But this isn't a confession?
Before I tell you who did it.
and you decide what to do about it.
you need to know
who could've done it
and why.
- Okay. why do I need to know that?
- 'Cause no one's innocent.
Violence begets violence.
it just doesn't always look the same.
How do you mean?
Some of us do
violence to ourselves.
Some try to break the pattern.
Zach tried.
Maybe Bryce was trying
to break the cycle within himself.
And Jessica found him
before he got the chance.
- Did you bring it?
- Yeah.
- Jess. seriously...
- Shh. No talking.
No.
this time I am talking.
Okay? I do not have time
to mess around.
Yeah. okay. I know.
I love you.
I don't want anything to happen to you.
And I'm scared.
Hey. Don't be scared.
Do you believe in me?
- I mean. do you really believe in me?
- Yes.
Of course I do.
Then we're gonna be okay.
Everyone had their reasons.
The trick was trying to tell
who just wanted Bryce dead.
and who could actually kill.
I mean.
what does a killer look like?
You know. I'm actually asking.
because... we had no idea.
But you had your suspicions?
Who among us would be most likely
to take a gun...
and pull the trigger?
Hey. man.
Hey. Alex.
Uh. Clay was looking for you.
I told him that you weren't in first.
Yeah. I'm kinda skipping today.
- Oh...
- But...
I heard about Monty being arrested.
And what he did to you.
Are you okay?
I mean. yeah.
That's really fucked up. I'm so sorry.
Thanks.
Listen. um...
Do you still have a gun?
No.
The last one I gave Clay.
that was all I had.
Why?
No. I just... Just don't want
those guys to come after you.
Monty's guys.
Well. if they wanna go to jail...
Right.
What are you working on?
Uh...
Holy shit. Tyler.
You took these as proof?
Yeah.
I only took one that first night.
I thought I would leave it behind
as proof.
And then. after that. I...
I started to take one a day.
Just to...
like. track the bruises. I guess.
I ended up tracking how I changed.
Over time.
♪ Thought I'd go and leave ♪
After Bryce died.
I almost quit.
But I kept going.
♪ All your life. all your life
All your life ♪
♪ All your life ♪
♪ All your life. all your life
All your life ♪
Talking to the police must've been
like a weight off. right?
Yeah. it was.
Hey...
are you okay?
Yeah. Yeah. I am.
♪ All your life. all your life
All your life ♪
So the false alarm at Spring Fling
wasn't a false alarm at all?
Okay.
you're going to tell me
why I shouldn't go arrest Tyler
right now.
Well. because this conversation
would be over.
And in a few minutes.
I'm going to tell you
exactly why you can't go
arrest Tyler.
He was the only one
who kept a gun?
He thought
he needed the power.
He thought it made him a man.
Does that really matter
to kids these days?
- Being a man?
-  I think you know it does.
Hey. Alex.
Hey. Where you going?
I have an appointment off-campus.
it's physical therapy.
- How're you gonna get there?
- My dad'll pick me up.
Your dad.
You're... you're gonna see your dad?
Yeah. I just texted him.
He should be here soon. Why?
Um...
I just talked to Tyler.
He told me you asked him for a gun.
Yeah. I just needed
to blow off some steam.
And I thought I'd do some target practice.
and my dad won't let me.
But anyway. he didn't have one. So...
Are you...
Is everything good?
Yeah. everything's fine.
Okay. And your dad's gonna pick you up
and you don't need. like. a ride?
No. Thanks.
Hey. Alex. Listen. actually... Do you have
one minute to talk before you go?
- About what?
- Look. I think Ani did it.
- And I can't cover for her anymore.
- You think Ani?
That's crazy.
Is it?
Because it wasn't me.
She's all that's left.
Alex was right.
nobody's clean.
I knew
Alex was using steroids.
But not from Bryce.
Monty was buying
from Bryce.
We didn't find anything
on Monty.
Does it surprise you
he might be a step ahead?
Maybe your sheriff
should have dug deeper.
But you were all briefly convinced
you had your man in Tony Padilla.
- Tony had a motive.
- He did.
He had more motive than you know.
Whoa. this is happening now?
Ani's talking to the cops
so I've got to be ready to move.
- Okay. Give me two minutes.
- I don't have it.
You're just gonna try
and convince me not to do this.
and we've had
this conversation plenty.
I swear I won't.
Just come outside.
If I don't make it to the police station
by this afternoon. they're coming here.
- You get me?
- I get you.
Now. come outside
before I pick a fight with you
and embarrass you in front of Javi.
Any other day. and I would
prove that statement ridiculous.
What are you gonna say outside
- you can't say in here?
- Not what I can say.
more what you can see.
Okay.
In retrospect.
this is probably a bad idea.
but it's already set in motion.
so you're just gonna
have to deal with it.
What the fuck am I gonna have
to deal with. Caleb?
- No. No.
- It's too late. it's done.
- Caleb.
- It's too late.
Now take the keys.
If you're gonna leave me.
then at least you'll have your first love.
So.
Tony did have a killer motive
we didn't even know about?
And you yourself came to think
that Clay could do it. now you don't.
You had tried to use Mr. Porter
and Mrs. Baker against him.
- But it worked the other way. didn't it?
- I think the sheriff
in the end felt
the case was helped
- by their interview.
- But you didn't think so.
Otherwise we wouldn't still
be sitting here.
So. just what I've learned today:
Tyler Down was almost
a school shooter.
Tony Padilla's
family was deported
because of Bryce
Walker's family.
and my own son went to a prostitute
with Bryce.
What else?
Well. of course you know
that Justin Foley's a drug addict?
No. I did not know that.
Well. you need to.
for where we're going.
I don't know.
Isn't this. like. against the law?
I don't know. I just...
It's what we have to do.
You're the only one who can do it.
You're his friend.
Can I ask you something?
Some of the guys. they're saying
you're. like. a drug addict.
That you do heroin.
That's not true. right?
Yeah. it's true.
I've made... a lot of mistakes. man.
Sometimes I feel like
that's all life is.
It's just
all the mistakes you make
and all the shit you gotta do
to set it right.
Justin was as good as his word.
He would defend Clay until the end.
Which was going
to get complicated.
- Or Clay would defend Justin.
- Or Tyler Down.
And keep his secrets.
Or Jessica Davis.
Or Zach Dempsey.
Or Alex Standall?
Look. it's complicated.
We need to make it simple.
I think...
I think I would
like that glass of water
now. if... if you don't mind.
Okay.
There you go.
So. we got about a dozen kids
who could've done it.
It's all about Homecoming night.
Everyone was there.
Everyone had their reasons
for wanting to kill Bryce.
At the end of the night. one of them
would have followed through.
Clay Jensen had been broken by Bryce
more than once.
Bryce had threatened to ruin Monty's life.
Jessica Davis was on fire with the cause.
with anger at Bryce.
Justin Foley would've done anything
for her.
Tony would've loved
to get into that fight.
Tyler felt under attack all over again.
And Zach's dreams were destroyed
with one hit.
So. he tried
to destroy Bryce's dreams.
- As you know. he didn't finish the job.
- So who did?
You all knew that Clay threatened Bryce
on the field.
- We did.
- And you know that Justin pulled him off.
- And sent him running.
- Where the fuck did he go?
- Yes.
- And how'd you know all this?
You talked to the other players. correct?
So. I imagine they told you that
Bryce and Monty also had words
on the field?
Go!
- Hey! Hey. that was fucking late!
- Says the king of the cheap shot!
- I'll break you if I have to.
- Go right ahead. man.
Come on. Luke.
- Get ready.
- Let's go.
Monty spent the whole night
literally trying to break Bryce in half.
- Good hit. Monty.
- Keep coming. Walker. Keep coming.
- Think you'll scare me?
- I'll fucking kill you.
Okay. buddy.
Listen. that thing we talked about.
You're all good.
Take care of yourself. man.
Walker!
What's up. Monty?
What the fuck
are you trying to prove?
I'm trying to prove
that I'm worth something in this world.
You should try it.
I gotta go.
I will take you out.
No. you won't.
'Cause you're just a coward.
you always have been.
Monty immediately got into his car
and followed the Hillcrest bus.
The fuck are you doing here?
Yearbook.
I'm in Yearbook. I was just... I'm going.
Hey. Hey...
I ain't gonna do anything.
I gotta go.
Listen. man.
I'm sorry about last summer.
I was drunk. and really fucked up.
It's fine.
I mean. whatever.
You...
seem like a good guy.
Um...
You want...
My parents are gone all weekend...
if you want to hang out?
Monty followed that bus
as soon as it left Liberty.
Holy shit!
Are you gonna beat the shit
out of me now?
I said I was sorry.
I know. I was just making a joke.
I'll give you a ride somewhere
if you don't want to Uber.
Are you trying to kick me out?
No. I just figured you'd want to go.
Well. maybe...
I want to stay and do that again.
Yeah?
Okay.
I'm not fucking gay.
Cool.
You can be whatever you want to be.
No.
I can't.
Monty had a secret.
Bryce knew what it was.
The secret being his assault on Tyler?
- Yes.
- And that would drive Montgomery
- to kill him?
- That. and a betrayal.
He thought
Bryce was his brother.
No. Monty had an alibi.
Talk to Charlie St. George.
It won't hold up.
So. you're telling me...
You're telling me Montgomery de la Cruz?
Process of elimination.
Jessica was home in bed.
Her dad tucked her in.
Okay. last message.
I need you and I don't know
where the fuck you are. but I'm worried.
I... I need you. Can you just...
Can you please call me back?
Hey!
Hi. um...
Could you sneak out right now?
And while she was sleeping...
Justin was out getting high.
He bought from a dealer named Halls.
out on the waterfront by Whitley Docks.
He got blackout high right there.
We can check that.
Whitley Dock is covered
with security cameras.
Check it.
I suppose they've got cameras
up and down the waterfront.
Then you should look for
Tony Padilla.
He wasn't home in bed
with his boyfriend.
He was out waiting for a fixer.
A guy who works for a local dealer
hooked into a Mexican cartel.
Camarillo thinks I'm dealing.
You tell him I'm dealing mufflers.
shocks and tires.
He wants to talk to you.
- Tell him I'm taking care of my family.
- Hey!
- He wants to talk to you.
- What. like. now?
Fuck me.
You're telling me
that Tony was laundering drug money?
He was laundering
garage money.
Sending cash south
to his family.
because Bryce's lawyer
had ruined their lives.
But Tony was two miles upriver
when Bryce died.
- Any idea where my son was?
- Alex?
Alex went out to meet Tyler.
not Jessica.
Alex knew Tyler was upset
after the fight.
He didn't want you to know why.
They met at Rosie's Diner.
And Clay Jensen?
Clay Jensen was with me.
He never told you
because he was protecting me.
I saw his car
at the Chatham house.
I told him
we had to get out of there.
I got in the car
and drove around with him all night.
Talking him down.
And Monty followed Bryce?
Yes. Monty followed Bryce.
But he saw Zach's car. so he waited
down at the end of the main pier.
Monty saw Zach drive out of there.
headlights off. Fast.
He waited another minute or two.
Then he drove down the pier
to confront Bryce.
What the fuck are you doing here?
What happened to you?
Fucking Zach.
Wow. he kinda beat the shit out of you.
Why are you here?
He's with me.
Hey. Jess. You came.
Yep.
So. what did you want to give me?
I made you a tape.
Is that some stupid fucking joke?
No. No. no. no. no. no.
Hang on. Hang on.
Fuck!
Fuck. Sorry. it's got...
There's some blood on the case.
Here. please take it. Take it.
- What's on it?
- A confession.
And an apology.
It owns up to everything I did.
You can play it for whoever you want.
Or nobody.
If you could maybe play it for Mrs. Baker.
though. She didn't want to talk to me.
And that came as a surprise to you?
I'm trying to set things right.
I'm trying to be better.
but this fucking world won't let me.
This world won't let you.
What the fuck does that mean. Bryce?
Nobody believes I can change.
Clearly the fucking judge did.
Wait. guys.
Guys. wait. Wait. please.
I can't walk.
I can't even stand up.
Can you help me get home?
Or to a hospital?
Why not sleep under the stars
and. you know.
meditate on how hard it is
to get the world to let you change?
Jess. please.
Jess. wa... Alex. Alex!
Guys. it's the middle of the fucking river
in November.
It's gonna be fucking freezing tonight
and I'm wet.
and I'm coughing blood.
- Jess.
- If we help him. Zach goes to jail.
If we leave him and he freezes to death.
Zach definitely goes to jail.
For fuck's sake. you guys. Please!
Please. I don't want to die out here.
Alex! Alex. please.
Come on. we were... we were friends.
We were never friends.
Here.
Monty's conscience stirred
and he went back to help Bryce.
But Bryce was in a fury of pain.
Fucking Zach!
I'm gonna fuck up his other knee
and wreck his fucking life!
You're not going to do anything
to Zach.
I'm gonna fucking destroy him!
You! You set me up!
She did not set you up!
She fucking set me up!
And in that moment. helping him up.
Monty looked into his eyes.
You've hurt everyone I ever loved.
Monty realized that
the cycle had to be broken somehow.
Alex. what the fuck?
And all those years
of being manipulated. all the rage.
the hurt. burst out of him.
Shit!
Alex!
Alex. fuck! Help!
Help me! I can't...
Help me! Help. I can't...
♪ You said you won't break my heart ♪
♪ Unless you do ♪
Hey.
It's gonna be fine. No one knows.
I love you.
You can't say that.
You can't say that
ever again.
We have to stay apart.
Monty drove home alone.
knowing he would have to live
with what he's done.
So. let's go through
how you know what you know.
First. Bryce and Monty's interaction
during the game
and at the team bus.
I told you. I pay attention.
I listen.
I can't tell you my sources. but...
if you go back to Zach Dempsey.
I'm sure he'll confirm the story.
And Alex was with Tyler?
I would do anything for Alex.
Or Clay. Or Jessica.
Anything.
And Tony Padilla.
what happens if I bring him in?
You won't.
He won't come after you.
He can't.
But I need the real story.
- That he can verify.
- If this works...
If. This is pretty fucked up.
But the whole thing's fucked up. Tony.
We don't have anything
to tie Monty to the scene.
Bryce had something
he wanted to give to Jessica.
Did you find anything?
On the pier? On his body?
No.
If you search through Monty's things.
his room...
perhaps his football locker...
I imagine you'll find it.
And I imagine
Bryce's blood will be on it.
We already searched his locker.
For steroids.
♪ Until the end ♪
Okay. I've got footprints.
I've got tire treads
consistent with my wife's car.
And she was at home in bed
all night.
He wouldn't have gone
to the pier alone.
He wouldn't have been alone.
Deputy Standall.
I've watched these kids
all year.
You may think they're divided
against each other.
They're not.
When someone needs them.
they'll be there.
No question.
They take care of each other.
So. Alex would've been there
for a friend.
For a friend who was maybe more injured
by Bryce than he was.
Or Monty was.
Whose life had been destroyed by Bryce...
and who's had to rebuild it.
Piece by piece.
I see.
Alex wouldn't have been alone.
Montgomery de la Cruz
killed Bryce Walker.
It would be a terrible thing to blame
the wrong person for Bryce's murder.
And yet you were all ready
to blame Clay Jensen.
I don't think
you would know this.
because the sheriff has us locked down
on leaks.
but Montgomery de la Cruz was killed
in his jail cell.
Just hours ago.
Dear God.
Poor Monty.
Even the dead
deserve the truth.
I am sorry
that Monty's dead.
I am.
Justin tells me he could be... loyal...
and fearless.
And that he stood up
for his friends.
I'm sorry that Bryce is dead.
He was my friend.
and I believe he would've shown the world
that redemption is possible.
But they both caused pain
while they were alive.
They caused great pain
to a number of people.
And it is time for that suffering
to end.
So. let the dead bury the dead.
Deputy Standall.
Let the dead bury the dead.
It's fucked up about Monty.
How did Ani know?
Well. Tim Pozzi was in the County lock-up
when it happened.
And he ended up getting out that morning.
so he told Luke.
who told Charlie. Charlie. Justin.
Justin to Ani.
Poor Monty. I mean.
I can't believe I'm saying that. but...
You...
asked Tyler for a gun today?
Yeah. I...
I wrote a confession.
And...
I... I don't know.
Jesus.
- Alex...
- I'm sorry I couldn't tell you.
I-I think...
we should be the kind of friends
who can tell each other anything.
I mean. maybe not about the hard-ons
and the masturbation so much. but...
So. what do we do now?
We wait.
We hope.
It's kinda too bad
that you don't have the tape.
I mean. for last words and all that.
We made a copy.
Look. I didn't mean...
- We don't have to...
- No.
I think you guys should hear it.
My dad put in a tape deck.
I think he thought it was funny.
Hey. Jess.
It's me.
Yeah. I know. A tape.
Yes. I did it on purpose.
Not to be a dick. but...
because the day I listened to those tapes.
my life changed.
And I bet the same is true for you.
And for Justin. and Zach. everyone.
And... I wanted to give you this.
I thought you'd hear me better
if I wasn't standing in front of you.
You said I had no idea
what I'd done to you.
You were right.
I can't stop thinking about you.
Um...
replaying that night in my mind.
I raped you.
I heard you say no. and...
I did it anyway.
Because I wanted to.
and I didn't care how you felt.
Justin tried to stop me.
I wish I could tell you
that there was a...
a tiny voice in my head telling me
that what I was doing to you was wrong.
There wasn't.
I never had one of those before.
That's not an excuse. it just... is.
I raped Hannah Baker.
I raped... seven or eight other girls.
Some of them were my girlfriends
at the time.
I won't name them. but if they choose
to tell you. believe them.
I'm broken.
I know that.
I'm a person
in a thousand pieces.
But I'm seeing a counselor.
It's a long. hard process. but...
little by little.
you start picking up the pieces.
And you realize
that what you're making is a mirror.
And the more pieces you put together.
the more you see yourself.
I'd like to say
that I'm not the same person
who raped you...
anymore. Jess.
But what I've come to realize is
that I'll always be him.
But I'm trying to be better.
To be someone worth something
in this world.
I-I have this dream that I could be
someone who protects people somehow.
Protects them from people like me.
like who I was. I don't know.
I am...
so...
fucking sorry
for what I did to you.
And I know words add up to nothing
compared to what I took from you.
Someone once told me that it'll take me
a lifetime to learn what sorry is.
They're right.
But I'm starting.
If you've listened this far.
thank you.
It's more than I deserve.
I wouldn't blame you if you smashed
this tape to fucking pieces. I would.
I wish you the best. Jess.
Truly.
Goodbye.
What happens to us now?
You mean. like. all of us?
- I don't know.
- No. Me and you.
Nothing has to happen.
I love you.
How can you?
It's...
It's the only way I know.
How can you look at me
and not see somebody...
different?
Can you look at me and not see the boy...
who let Bryce rape you?
No.
So?
Justin. I'm afraid.
I know.
Alex?
Dad. what is it?
Well. the sheriff and the prosecutor
think they have enough evidence
to close the case file on Bryce Walker.
He was killed by Montgomery de la Cruz.
Oh.
And Montgomery's dead. so...
case closed.
Okay.
Wow. Okay.
You know. son. when I found you
last year on the bathroom floor...
I wished that bullet was in my head.
not yours.
Do you understand?
Yeah. I understand.
I love you. son.
I love you too. Dad.
My boy.
♪ The perfect place may never exist
May never exist ♪
♪ The perfect time might be years
And years away ♪
♪ The city is overweight
And it's pressing on the pair of us ♪
♪ We scowl and sweat
Beneath the overbearing crush ♪
♪ But I still want to be here
Want to be here ♪
♪ I still want to be here
♪ And I would live in a devil's ditch
Just to be near you ♪
♪ I still want to be here
Want to be here ♪
I'm telling you. Caleb did everything.
He even made the masa himself.
Mijo. are you sure
the Jensens like tamales?
Everyone likes tamales!
We miss you. Tonio.
- We miss you! Tonio!
- Hey!
Wish you were here. man.
Your asshole brother's already drunk.
- Caleb.
- Caleb...
Happy Thanksgiving. Mr. Padilla.
Arturo. please.
Caleb.
I'm sorry
we didn't get to meet in person.
I am. too.
Soon. I hope.
Even from far away.
you are family.
You understand me?
Yes. sir. Thank you.
You two take care of each other.
okay?
We will.
I promise.
Heavenly Father. we thank you
for this wonderful food.
For our families. Lord.
and for our friends.
and all of your abundant blessings.
Father. please bless
and keep safe our children.
All of our children.
Their world is darker than ours.
And. Father. forgive us
for what we've done to make it that way.
May God keep us all and help us
to be truly grateful
for our life and our freedom.
This we ask in the name
of Christ our Heavenly Father.
- Amen.
Caleb and Tony.
we're not a religious family.
but we can say a prayer. if you'd like?
I gave up on the Catholics
when they gave up on us. Mrs. Jensen.
I'm a recovering Baptist myself.
Well. our tradition is
to just go around the table
and say what we're thankful for.
I'm thankful for having so many people
around the table.
I am thankful for Tony.
Uh. I'm...
thankful that family can be...
where you find it.
I am thankful that Clay is here.
and that he has so many people
that care about him.
Uh. I'm...
thankful to...
to have family at all.
And...
I... I haven't stayed clean...
all this time.
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry for lying to you guys.
And I...
I probably need more help.
I didn't mean to bring...
bring the mood down.
We will get you whatever help you need.
Justin.
We promise.
I. um...
I'm thankful to be here
with all of you.
And. um...
I'm thankful
to be alive.
Amen!
- Amen! Let's eat!
- Yeah.
Yes?
Sorry. Ani said no one was home.
I've just come home.
From talking to the sheriff.
Oh.
You must be very relieved.
I am.
I'm... I'm also very sorry for your loss.
Mrs. Walker.
I'm sorry that Bryce is gone.
I don't think
I said that before.
You did.
But I'm not sure
you meant it then.
Ani...
Ani tells me
you're a good young man.
I'm trying to be. Mrs. Walker.
I'm...
really trying hard.
Your... your daughter is. uh...
very important to me.
I-I just...
I'd like to make sure you know that
I would never do anything to hurt her.
And she's very brave.
Amorowat is a stubborn girl.
She leads
with her heart.
- Sometimes even into danger.
- Yes.
I'm afraid
we both have that in common.
But I...
I would do anything
to protect her.
Not that she needs me to.
obviously.
Other way round.
She offered to lie for you.
To lie to the police.
say you were with her.
- Uh...
- I'm not asking.
I know this. I heard it.
But you would not let her.
No. I didn't want her to.
Would you like some tea. perhaps?
While you wait.
Yeah. please. Thank you.
Mum?
This is Clay Jensen.
We're dating.
Amorowat.
have you not learned?
I know all this already.
Did we do the right thing?
Would the right thing have been
for you to go to jail?
Alex?
All the choices were wrong.
We had to choose one.
Thank you
for saving my life.
I saved you
from a long trial. maybe.
No.
Thank you
for saving my life.
Mrs. Walker.
- I'm afraid...
- I know.
- Should I alert the on-call doctor?
- It's Thanksgiving.
We'll call tomorrow
if need be.
- Thank you.
- Ruth?
Ruthie?
It's Nora. Dad.
Nora...
Are you in any pain?
No.
I tried to give you
the best life I could. Nora.
I wanted you to have better things
than I had.
I know. Dad.
I did the best I knew how.
No one taught me better.
I know.
All right. everybody. Everybody!
Come on.
Hey... uh...
I caught Tyler taking my picture
a few months ago
while I was working.
And I wanted to go all...
Alec Baldwin on him.
Until I saw the picture.
I told him he should do an exhibit
here at Monet's.
And he finally agreed.
So. here's Tyler.
- Come on. Tyler!
- Yeah!
Uh...
Hi. um...
So. there's a picture of everyone
that's helped me this year.
And I wanted to say thank you.
Uh...
Having friends
is an amazing thing.
Yeah.
That's incredible.
That's so cool.
♪ Hey now. little speedyhead ♪
♪ The read on the speed-meter says ♪
♪ You have to go to task in the city ♪
♪ Where people drown and people serve ♪
♪ Don't be shy.
your just deserve ♪
♪ Is only just light years to go ♪
♪ Me. my thoughts are flower strewn ♪
♪ Ocean storm. bayberry moon ♪
♪ I have got to leave
to find my way ♪
Why do you have me up there?
I can take it down.
if you want?
No. no. it's a...
great photo.
It actually makes me seem good-looking.
so...
Holy shit. dude.
You know you're good-looking. right?
Whatever.
Uh...
Listen. I just. I wanted to say...
I am so sorry
about what happened to you.
And I'm sorry that
I didn't know about it.
I don't know
what would have been different. but...
I would like to think that if I'd known.
I would've had the guts to...
to do something
to make your life not hell.
And the amount that I contributed to that.
to your life being hell. over the years.
I am so... so sorry.
Yeah. No. it's cool.
- Thank you.
- Yeah.
♪ But nothing is going my way ♪
You know I'll always love you.
right?
You're the best friend
I've ever had.
- I'm sorry for everything.
- No.
I refuse to be sorry.
or let you.
How are we going to live
with this?
We're survivors.
you and me.
FML forever?
FML forever.
♪ The river to the ocean goes
A fortune for the undertow ♪
♪ None of this is going my way ♪
What did you tell the cops?
- Look. Winston...
- He didn't kill Bryce.
He was with me.
- What'd you tell 'em?
- Winston...
- He was already gone.
- He was a human being.
Okay? He was a human being.
He didn't deserve
to die like that.
I know.
Nothing can just be easy. can it?
Isn't that kinda the point?
I mean. how is it the point?
For some people. it's easy.
Like Bryce. I always thought...
it was easy for him.
Life was easy.
Look how that ended up.
Yeah. See?
It's not supposed to be easy
for people like us.
We're... meant to go through shit and...
make it out alive.
That's the trick.
you have to make it out alive.
You know what? I want better than that.
We've been through so much shit
and I just want something different.
I want more.
I'm with you.
We deserve
some fucking happiness.
- Yeah. we do.
- Yes. we do.
I love you guys!
Oh. my God. Shut up!
Way to ruin the moment.
I'm embracing the moment.
- Can you get me some more coffee. please?
- Yeah. in a minute.
- This couch is really comfy.
- So comfy!
I'm so tired.
♪ Crazy. some'd say ♪
♪ Where is the life that I recognize? ♪
♪ Gone away
And I won't cry for yesterday ♪
♪ There's an ordinary world
Somehow I have to find ♪
For help finding crisis resources.
visit 13reasonswhy.info.
♪ To the ordinary world ♪
♪ I will learn to survive ♪
♪ Passion or coincidence
Once prompted you to say ♪
♪ Pride will tear us both apart ♪
♪ Well now pride's gone out the window
♪ Cross the rooftops run away ♪
♪ Left me in the vacuum of my heart ♪
♪ Would this happen to me? ♪
♪ Crazy some would say ♪
♪ Where is my friend
When I need you most? ♪
♪ Gone away
And I won't cry for yesterday ♪
♪ There's an ordinary world ♪
♪ Somehow I have to find ♪
♪ And as I try to make my way ♪
♪ To the ordinary world ♪
♪ I will learn to survive ♪
Well done. Ed. well done.